There's a group of people in Kenya.
هناك مجموعة من الناس في كينيا.
People cross oceans to go see them.
يَعبُر الناس المحيطات لرؤيتهم.
These people are tall.
هؤلاء الناس هم طَوِيلِي القامة.
They jump high. They wear red.
انهم يقفزون عاليا. انهم يلبسون الأحمر.
And they kill lions.
يقومون بقتل الأُسُود.
You might be wondering, who are these people?
يمكن أن تتساءل، من هم هؤلاء الناس؟
These are the Maasais.
هذه هي قبائل المَاسَاي.
And you know what's cool? I'm actually one of them.
هل تَعلَم ما الرائع؟ أنا في الواقع واحد منهم.
The Maasais, the boys are brought up to be warriors.
المَاسَاي، تَتِم تربية الأولاد لجعلهم محاربين.
The girls are brought up to be mothers.
تَتِم تربية الفتيات على أن يصبحن أمهات.
When I was five years old,
عندما كان عمري خمس سنوات،
I found out that I was engaged
اِكتشفت أنني كنت مخطوبة
to be married as soon as I reached puberty.
و سأتزوج بمجرد وصولي سن البلوغ.
My mother, my grandmother, my aunties,
أمي، وجدتي، واعمامي،
they constantly reminded me that
يذكّرونَني باستمرار أن
your husband just passed by.
زَوجَكِ مرّ من هنا.
(Laughter) Cool, yeah?
(ضحك) رائع، نعم؟
And everything I had to do from that moment
وكل ما كان علي القيام به من تلك اللحظة
was to prepare me to be a perfect woman at age 12.
كان إعدادي لأكون امرأة مثالية في سن الـ 12.
My day started at 5 in the morning,
يبدأ يومي الساعة 5 صباحا،
milking the cows, sweeping the house,
حلب الأبقار، كنس البيت،
cooking for my siblings, collecting water, firewood.
الطبخ لإخوتي، وجمع المياه والحطب.
I did everything that I needed to do
لقد فعلت كل ما كنت بحاجة للقيام
to become a perfect wife.
لٱصبح زوجة مثالية.
I went to school not because the Maasais'
ذهابي إلى المدرسة ليس بِسبَبِ
women or girls were going to school.
نساء أوفتيات المَاسَاي اللواتي كُنّ يَذهَبن إلى المدرسة.
It's because my mother was denied an education,
بل لأن أمي حُرِمت من التعليم،
and she constantly reminded me and my siblings that
فكانت تُذَكِّرني باسمرار و إخوتي كذلك
she never wanted us to live the life she was living.
على أنها لم ترغب لنا أن نعيش الحياة التي عاشتها.
Why did she say that?
لماذا قالت ذلك؟
My father worked as a policeman in the city.
والدي عَمِل كشرطي في المدينة.
He came home once a year.
يعود إلى موطنه مرة كل السنة.
We didn't see him for sometimes even two years.
نحن لا نراه أحيانا لمدة تتجاوز السنتين.
And whenever he came home, it was a different case.
وكلما أتى المنزل، كان حالة مختلفة.
My mother worked hard in the farm
والدتي عملت بجد في المزرعة
to grow crops so that we can eat.
لزراعة المحاصيل حتى أنه يمكننا أن نأكل.
She reared the cows and the goats
وقالت أنها تربى الأبقار والماعز
so that she can care for us.
لذا يمكن أن الرعاية أنها بالنسبة لنا.
But when my father came, he would sell the cows,
ولكن عندما جاء والدي، قال أن بيع الأبقار،
he would sell the products we had,
أنه سوف تبيع المنتجات التي أجريناها،
and he went and drank with his friends in the bars.
وذهب ويشرب مع أصدقائه في الحانات.
Because my mother was a woman,
لأن والدتي كانت امرأة،
she was not allowed to own any property,
وقالت أنها لم يسمح بتملك أي ممتلكات،
and by default, everything in my family anyway
بشكل افتراضي، كل شيء في عائلتي، وعلى أي حال
belongs to my father, so he had the right.
ينتمي إلى والدي، ذلك أنه كان الحق.
And if my mother ever questioned him,
وإذا كان من أي وقت مضى وتساءل والدتي له،
he beat her, abused her, and really it was difficult.
أنه يضربها، يسيء معاملتها، ومن الصعب حقاً.
When I went to school, I had a dream.
عندما ذهبت إلى المدرسة، كان لدى حلم.
I wanted to become a teacher.
أردت أن تصبح معلمة.
Teachers looked nice.
المعلمين تتطلع لطيفة.
They wear nice dresses, high-heeled shoes.
أنهم ارتداء فستان لطيفة، أحذية ذات الكعب العالي.
I found out later that they are uncomfortable, but I admired it.
اكتشفت لاحقاً أنهم غير مريحة، ولكن أنا معجب بذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But most of all, the teacher was just writing on the board --
ولكن الأهم من ذلك كله، كان مجرد كتابة المعلم في المجلس-
not hard work, that's what I thought,
ليس من الصعب العمل، وذلك ما فكرت به،
compared to what I was doing in the farm.
مقارنة بما كانت تقوم به في المزرعة.
So I wanted to become a teacher.
لذا أردت أن تصبح معلمة.
I worked hard in school, but when I was in eighth grade,
عملت بجد في المدرسة، ولكن عندما كنت في الصف الثامن،
it was a determining factor.
كان عاملاً حاسما.
In our tradition, there is a ceremony
في تقاليدنا، هناك حفل
that girls have to undergo to become women,
أن تضطر الفتيات إلى الخضوع لتصبح المرأة،
and it's a rite of passage to womanhood.
وطقوس للأنوثة.
And then I was just finishing my eighth grade,
وثم أنا كان مجرد الانتهاء من بلدي الصف الثامن،
and that was a transition for me to go to high school.
وكان ذلك تحول بالنسبة لي للذهاب إلى المدرسة الثانوية.
This was the crossroad.
وكان هذا مفترق طرق.
Once I go through this tradition, I was going to become a wife.
مرة واحدة ذهبت من خلال هذا التقليد، كنت ذاهبا لتصبح زوجة.
Well, my dream of becoming a teacher will not come to pass.
حسنا، لن يأتي حلمي أن تصبح معلمة لتمرير.
So I talked -- I had to come up with a plan
حيث تحدثت-اضطررت إلى الخروج بخطة
to figure these things out.
لمعرفة هذه الأمور.
I talked to my father. I did something that most girls have never done.
لقد تحدثت إلى والدي. لم أكن شيئا أن لم تفعل معظم الفتيات.
I told my father, "I will only go through this ceremony
قلت لوالدي، "سوف اذهب فقط من خلال هذا الحفل
if you let me go back to school."
إذا كنت اسمحوا لي أن نعود إلى المدرسة. "
The reason why, if I ran away,
والسبب لماذا، إذا جريت بعيداً،
my father will have a stigma, people will be calling him
والدي سيكون وصمة عار، والناس سوف تكون الدعوة له
the father of that girl who didn't go through the ceremony.
والد تلك الفتاة التي لم تذهب من خلال الحفل.
It was a shameful thing for him to carry the rest of his life.
أنه شيء مخجل لآلية لتنفيذ بقية حياته.
So he figured out. "Well," he said, "okay,
حيث أنه اكتشف. فقال "حسنا,"، قال، "تمام،
you'll go to school after the ceremony."
عليك الذهاب إلى المدرسة بعد الحفل. "
I did. The ceremony happened.
فعلت ذلك. الاحتفال بحدث.
It's a whole week long of excitement.
أسبوع كامل فترة طويلة من الإثارة.
It's a ceremony. People are enjoying it.
واحتفال. الناس يتمتعون بذلك.
And the day before the actual ceremony happens,
وفي اليوم السابق للحفل الفعلي يحدث،
we were dancing, having excitement,
ونحن كانت الرقص، ووجود الإثارة،
and through all the night we did not sleep.
ومن خلال كل ليلة ونحن لا ينام.
The actual day came, and we walked out of the house
وجاء اليوم الفعلي، ومشينا الخروج من المنزل
that we were dancing in. Yes, we danced and danced.
أن علينا الرقص في. نعم، نحن رقصت ورقصت.
We walked out to the courtyard, and there were a bunch of people waiting.
مشيناً إلى الفناء، وكانت هناك حفنة من الناس ينتظرون.
They were all in a circle.
وكانوا جميعا في حلقة مفرغة.
And as we danced and danced,
وكما أننا رقصت، ورقصت،
and we approached this circle of women,
واقترب من هذه الدائرة من النساء،
men, women, children, everybody was there.
الرجال والنساء والأطفال، وكان الجميع هناك.
There was a woman sitting in the middle of it,
وكان هناك امرأة تجلس في وسطها،
and this woman was waiting to hold us.
وكان في انتظار هذه المرأة تحمل بنا.
I was the first. There were my sisters and a couple of other girls,
كان الأول. كانت هناك اخواتي وزوجين من غيرها من الفتيات،
and as I approached her,
واقتراب لها،
she looked at me, and I sat down.
وقالت أنها تتطلع في وجهي، وجلست.
And I sat down, and I opened my legs.
وجلست وفتحت ساقي.
As I opened my leg, another woman came,
كما فتحت ساقي، جاءت امرأة أخرى،
and this woman was carrying a knife.
وهذه المرأة كانت تحمل سكينا.
And as she carried the knife, she walked toward me
وكما أنها قامت السكين، وهي تسير نحو لي
and she held the clitoris, and she cut it off.
وقالت أنها عقدت البظر، وقالت أنها قطعت.
As you can imagine, I bled. I bled.
كما يمكنك أن تتخيل، أنا نزفت. أنا نزفت.
After bleeding for a while, I fainted thereafter.
بعد النزيف لفترة من الوقت، أنا أغمي على وبعد ذلك.
It's something that so many girls --
وأمر أن الكثير من الفتيات-
I'm lucky, I never died -- but many die.
أنا محظوظ، مات ابدأ-لكن يموت كثير.
It's practiced, it's no anesthesia, it's a rusty old knife,
هو يمارس، هو ليس التخدير، أنها سكين قديمة صدئة،
and it was difficult.
وكان من الصعب.
I was lucky because one, also, my mom did something
لقد كنت محظوظاً لأن واحد، أيضا، أمي فعلت شيئا
that most women don't do.
أن معظم النساء لا تفعل.
Three days later, after everybody has left the home,
ثلاثة أيام في وقت لاحق، بعد أن الجميع قد غادر المنزل،
my mom went and brought a nurse.
أمي ذهبت وجلبت ممرضة.
We were taken care of.
ونحن تم الاعتناء بنا.
Three weeks later, I was healed, and I was back in high school.
بعد ثلاثة أسابيع، كنت قد شفيت، وعدت مرة أخرى للمدرسة الثانوية.
I was so determined to be a teacher now
كنت مصممة لذلك أن يكون معلم الآن
so that I could make a difference in my family.
حتى أنه يمكن أن فرقا في عائلتي.
Well, while I was in high school, something happened.
حسنا، بينما كنت في المدرسة الثانوية، حدث شيء.
I met a young gentleman from our village
التقيت برجل شاب من قريتنا
who had been to the University of Oregon.
الذين كان لجامعة ولاية أوريغون.
This man was wearing a white t-shirt, jeans, camera,
هذا الرجل كان يرتدي قميصا أبيض، الچينز، وكاميرا،
white sneakers -- and I'm talking about white sneakers.
أحذية رياضية بيضاء-وأنا أتحدث عن أحذية رياضية بيضاء.
There is something about clothes, I think, and shoes.
هناك شيء حول الملابس، أعتقد، وأحذية.
They were sneakers, and this is in a village
كانت أحذية رياضية، وهذا في قرية
that doesn't even have paved roads. It was quite attractive.
أنه لا يملك حتى الطرق المعبدة. أنها كانت جذابة للغاية.
I told him, "Well, I want to go to where you are,"
قلت له: "حسنا، أريد أن اذهب إلى أين أنت،"
because this man looked very happy, and I admired that.
لأن هذا الرجل بدأ سعيداً جداً، وأنا معجب بهذا.
And he told me, "Well,
وقال لي، "حسنا،
what do you mean, you want to go?
ماذا تقصد، وتريد أن تذهب؟
Don't you have a husband waiting for you?"
لا يكون لديك زوج تنتظر منك؟ "
And I told him, "Don't worry about that part.
وقلت له: "لا تقلق بشأن ذلك الجزء.
Just tell me how to get there."
قل لي فقط كيفية الوصول إلى هناك. "
This gentleman, he helped me.
هذا الرجل، ساعدني.
While I was in high school also, my dad was sick.
بينما كنت في المدرسة الثانوية أيضا، أن والدي كان مريضا.
He got a stroke, and he was really, really sick,
حصل السكتة دماغية، وأنه كان حقاً، حقاً مريضة،
so he really couldn't tell me what to do next.
حتى أنه حقاً لا يمكن أن يقول لي ما يجب القيام به المرة المقبلة.
But the problem is, my father is not the only father I have.
ولكن المشكلة هي، والدي ليس الأب الوحيد لدى.
Everybody who is my dad's age, male in the community,
الجميع الذي هو سن والدي، الذكور في المجتمع،
is my father by default --
هو والدي بشكل افتراضي-
my uncles, all of them -- and they dictate what my future is.
بلادي الأعمام، كل منهم--وأنها تملي ما مستقبلي.
So the news came, I applied to school
حيث جاءت الأنباء، تقدمت بطلب للمدرسة
and I was accepted to Randolph-Macon Woman's College in Lynchburg, Virginia,
وكانت قد قبلت بكلية راندولف ماكون "امرأة" في لينشبيرغ، ڨيرچينيا،
and I couldn't come without the support of the village,
وأنا لا يمكنني أن المجيء من دون دعم القرية،
because I needed to raise money to buy the air ticket.
لأنني في حاجة لجمع الأموال لشراء التذاكر الجوية.
I got a scholarship but I needed to get myself here.
حصلت على منحة دراسية ولكن كنت بحاجة للحصول على نفسي هنا.
But I needed the support of the village,
ولكن أنا بحاجة إلى دعم القرية،
and here again, when the men heard,
وهنا مرة أخرى، عندما سمع الرجل،
and the people heard that a woman had gotten an opportunity to go to school,
وسمع الناس أن المرأة قد حصلت على فرصة للذهاب إلى المدرسة،
they said, "What a lost opportunity.
قالوا: "يا لها من فرصة ضائعة.
This should have been given to a boy. We can't do this."
هذه الفرصة كانت ينبغي أن تكون لصبي. ونحن لا يمكن القيام بذلك. "
So I went back and I had to go back to the tradition.
فعدت واضطررت إلى العودة إلى التقاليد.
There's a belief among our people
وثمة اعتقاد بين أبناء شعبنا
that morning brings good news.
أن الصباح يجلب أنباء طيبة.
So I had to come up with something to do with the morning,
لذا اضطررت إلى الخروج لفعل شيئا مع الصباح،
because there's good news in the morning.
لأن هناك أخبار جيدة في الصباح.
And in the village also, there is one chief, an elder,
وفي القرية أيضا، هناك رئيس واحد، الأكبر،
who if he says yes, everybody will follow him.
الذي إذا قال نعم، الجميع سوف يرضخ.
So I went to him very early in the morning, as the sun rose.
فذهبت إليه مبكرا جداً في الصباح، مع إرتفاع الشمس.
The first thing he sees when he opens his door is, it's me.
أول شيء يرى أنه عندما قال أنه يفتح باب منزله، أنها لي.
"My child, what are you doing here?"
"طفلي، ماذا تفعل هنا؟"
"Well, Dad, I need help. Can you support me to go to America?"
"حسنا، يا أبي، أحتاج إلى مساعدة. يمكن لك دعم لي للذهاب إلى أمريكا؟ "
I promised him that I would be the best girl,
تعهدت له أن أكون فتاة أفضل،
I will come back, anything they wanted after that,
وسوف أعود، أي شيء يريدونه بعد ذلك،
I will do it for them.
أنا سأفعل ذلك لهم.
He said, "Well, but I can't do it alone."
وقال، "حسنا، ولكن أنا لا يمكنني القيام بذلك بمفردي."
He gave me a list of another 15 men that I went --
وقدم لي قائمة من 15 رجلاً آخر أن ذهبت-
16 more men -- every single morning
16 عدد أكبر من الرجال-كل صباح واحد
I went and visited them.
ذهب، وقمت بزيارة لهم.
They all came together.
جاؤوا معا.
The village, the women, the men, everybody came together
القرية، النساء، والرجال، وجاء الجميع معا
to support me to come to get an education.
لدعمي من أجل لحضور والحصول على تعليم.
I arrived in America. As you can imagine, what did I find?
وصلت إلى أمريكا. كما يمكنك أن تتخيل، ماذا أرى؟
I found snow!
لقد وجدت الثلج!
I found Wal-Marts, vacuum cleaners,
لقد وجدت وول-مارت، المكانس الكهربائية،
and lots of food in the cafeteria.
والكثير من المواد الغذائية في المقصف.
I was in a land of plenty.
كنت في أرض الوفرة.
I enjoyed myself, but during that moment while I was here,
وقد أستمتعت، خلال تلك اللحظة حين كنت هنا، ولكن
I discovered a lot of things.
لقد اكتشفت الكثير من الأشياء.
I learned that that ceremony that I went through
وعلمت أن هذا الاحتفال الذي حضرته
when I was 13 years old, it was called female genital mutilation.
عندما كان عمري الـ 13 ، كان يطلق عليه ممارسة تشويه الأعضاء التناسلية للإناث.
I learned that it was against the law in Kenya.
تعلمت أنه كان مخالفا للقانون في كينيا.
I learned that I did not have to trade part of my body
تعلمت أن لم أكن مضطرة لإتجار بجزءا من جسدي
to get an education. I had a right.
للحصول على تعليم. كنت على حق.
And as we speak right now, three million girls
وفيما نحن نتكلم الآن، 3 مليون من الفتيات
in Africa are at risk of going through this mutilation.
تتعرض لنفس مخاطر للذهاب من خلال هذا التشويه في أفريقيا.
I learned that my mom had a right to own property.
لقد علمت أن أمي كان لديها حق إمتلاك عقار.
I learned that she did not have to be abused
علمت أنها لم تكن مضطرة ليساء لها
because she is a woman.
لأنها امرأة.
Those things made me angry.
هذه الأشياء جعلتني غاضبة.
I wanted to do something.
أردت أن أفعل شيئا.
As I went back, every time I went,
كما ذهبت مرة أخرى، في كل مرة ذهبت،
I found that my neighbors' girls were getting married.
لقد وجدت أن الفتيات جيراني كانوا يتزوجون.
They were getting mutilated, and here,
وكان يتم ختانهن، وهنا،
after I graduated from here, I worked at the U.N.,
بعد أن تخرجت من هنا، عملت في الأمم المتحدة،
I went back to school to get my graduate work,
عدت إلى المدرسة لإتمام التخرج،
the constant cry of these girls was in my face.
وكان البكاء المستمر لهؤلاء الفتيات في وجهي.
I had to do something.
واضطررت إلى القيام بشيء ما.
As I went back, I started talking to the men,
وأنا أعود إلى الوراء، بدأت تتحدث إلى الرجال،
to the village, and mothers, and I said,
إلى القرية، والأمهات، وقال،
"I want to give back the way I had promised you
"أريد أن أعطى مرة أخرى بالطريقة التي كنت قد وعدتكم بها
that I would come back and help you. What do you need?"
أن أعود وأساعد. ماذا تحتاجون؟ "
As I spoke to the women, they told me,
وعندما تحدثت إلى النساء، قالوا لي،
"You know what we need? We really need a school for girls."
"أنت تعرف ماذا نحتاج؟ إننا حقاً نحتاج مدرسة للفتيات ".
Because there had not been any school for girls.
لأنه لم يكن هناك أي مدرسة للبنات.
And the reason they wanted the school for girls
والسبب في أنهم يريدون المدرسة للبنات
is because when a girl is raped when she's walking to school,
لأنه عندما تتعرض فتاة للاغتصاب في طريقها إلى المدرسة،
the mother is blamed for that.
تلام الأم لذلك.
If she got pregnant before she got married,
إذا حملت قبل الزواج،
the mother is blamed for that, and she's punished.
ينحى باللائمة على الأم ، وتعاقب.
She's beaten.
وتضرب.
They said, "We wanted to put our girls in a safe place."
وقالوا، "أردنا أن نضع بناتنا في مكان أمن".
As we moved, and I went to talk to the fathers,
وأثناء انتقالنا، ذهبت للتحدث مع الآباء،
the fathers, of course, you can imagine what they said:
إن الآباء، وبطبيعة الحال، يمكنك أن تتخيل ماذا قالوا:
"We want a school for boys."
"أننا نريد مدرسة للبنين".
And I said, "Well, there are a couple of men from my village
وقلت، "حسنا، هناك اثنين من الرجال من قريتي
who have been out and they have gotten an education.
الذين كانا بها، وأنهما قد حصلا على تعليم.
Why can't they build a school for boys,
لماذا لا يبنون مدرسة للبنين،
and I'll build a school for girls?"
وسأقوم ببناء مدرسة للبنات "؟
That made sense. And they agreed.
كان هذا منطقيا. واتفقوا.
And I told them, I wanted them to show me a sign of commitment.
وقلت لهم أريد لها أن تظهروا لي امارات على الالتزام.
And they did. They donated land where we built the girls' school.
وفعلوا. تبرعوا بثمن الأرض حيث قمنا ببناء مدرسة البنات.
We have.
لدينا.
I want you to meet one of the girls in that school.
أريدكم أن تقابلوا إحدى الفتيات في تلك المدرسة.
Angeline came to apply for the school,
وجاءت انچيلين للتقدم بطلب الإلتحاق بالمدرسة،
and she did not meet any criteria that we had.
وقالت أنها لا تفي بأي من المعايير التي وضعناها.
She's an orphan. Yes, we could have taken her for that.
كانت يتيمة. نعم، كان يمكن أن يتم قبولها لذلك السبب .
But she was older. She was 12 years old,
ولكنها قالت أنها الأكبر سنا. كان عمرها 12 سنة،
and we were taking girls who were in fourth grade.
ونحن قد أخذ الفتيات اللاتي هن في الصف الرابع.
Angeline had been moving from one place --
انچيلين كانت تنتقل من مكان -
because she's an orphan, she has no mother, she has no father --
لأنها يتيمة، فلم يمن لديها لا الأم، ولا الأب-
moving from one grandmother's house to another one,
الانتقال من بيت الجدة ثم لبيت آخر،
from aunties to aunties. She had no stability in her life.
من بيوت الخالات إلى ابيوت خالات أخريات. وقالت أنها لم ترى الاستقرار في حياتها.
And I looked at her, I remember that day,
ونظرت في وجهها، وأتذكر ذلك اليوم،
and I saw something beyond what I was seeing in Angeline.
ورأيت شيئا يتجاوز ما أشاهده في انچيلين.
And yes, she was older to be in fourth grade.
ونعم، كانت الأكبر سنا في الصف الرابع.
We gave her the opportunity to come to the class.
أعطينا لها الفرصة لتأتي إلى الفصل.
Five months later, that is Angeline.
بعد خمسة أشهر، وهذه هي انچيلين.
A transformation had begun in her life.
وقد بدأت عملية تحول في حياتها.
Angeline wants to be a pilot so she can fly around the world
انچيلين تريد أن تكون طيارا لتتمكن من الطيران في جميع أنحاء العالم
and make a difference.
وأن تحدث فرقا.
She was not the top student when we took her.
وقالت أنها لم تكن الطالب الأعلى تقديرا عندما تم قبولها.
Now she's the best student, not just in our school,
ولكنها الآن أفضل طالب، ليس فقط في مدرستنا،
but in the entire division that we are in.
ولكن على مستوى التقسيم ككل.
That's Sharon. That's five years later.
وهذه شارون. هذا بعد مرور خمس سنوات.
That's Evelyn. Five months later, that is the difference that we are making.
وهذه إيفلين. بعد خمسة أشهر، وهذا هو الفرق التي نحدثه.
As a new dawn is happening in my school,
وكما يشرق في مدرستي، فجر جديد
a new beginning is happening.
تحدث بداية جديدة.
As we speak right now, 125 girls will never be mutilated.
الأن و نحن نتحدث, هناك 125 فتاة لن يتم تشويهم جنسيا
One hundred twenty-five girls will not be married when they're 12 years old.
١٢٥ فتاة لن تتزوج في سن التانيه عشر
One hundred twenty-five girls are creating and achieving their dreams.
١٢٥ فتاة يصنعن و يحققن احلامهن
This is the thing that we are doing,
هذا ما نفعله
giving them opportunities where they can rise.
نعطيهن الفرصة ليرتقوا
As we speak right now, women are not being beaten
في هذه اللحظة، لا يوجد فتيات تضرب
because of the revolutions we've started in our community.
بسبب الثورة التي بدآناها في مجتمعنا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I want to challenge you today.
اريد آن اتحداكم اليوم
You are listening to me because you are here,
انتم تسمعوني اليوم لانكم هنا
very optimistic.
متفائلين
You are somebody who is so passionate.
انتم اشخاص شغوفين
You are somebody who wants to see a better world.
انتم اشخاص تريدون عالما افضل
You are somebody who wants to see that war ends, no poverty.
انتم اشخاص تريدون أن تنتهي الحرب و لا تريدون الفقر
You are somebody who wants to make a difference.
انتم اشخاص تآملون بالتغيير
You are somebody who wants to make our tomorrow better.
انتم اشخاص تريدون ان تجعلوا المستقبل افضل
I want to challenge you today that to be the first,
اريد آن اتحداكم لتكونوا الآوائل
because people will follow you.
لآن الناس سوف تتبعكم
Be the first. People will follow you.
كونوا الآوائل و الناس سوف تتبعكم
Be bold. Stand up. Be fearless. Be confident.
كونوا شجعان ، قفوا ، و ثقوا
Move out, because as you change your world,
لانه عندما تغير العالم
as you change your community,
و تغيروا مجتمعكم
as we believe that we are impacting one girl, one family,
و عندما نؤمن انتا نؤثر في حياة فتاة آو في عائلة
one village, one country at a time.
في قرية او في بلد
We are making a difference, so if you change your world,
فنحن نحدث فرقاً، و إذا غيرت العالم
you are going to change your community,
تكون قد غيرت مجتمعك
you are going to change your country,
و تكون قد غيرت بلدك
and think about that. If you do that, and I do that,
وفكر بهذا : إذا قمت بهذا و انا آيضاً
aren't we going to create a better future for our children,
حينها نصنع مستقبلاً آفضل من أجل أطفالنا
for your children, for our grandchildren?
وأحفادنا؟
And we will live in a very peaceful world. Thank you very much.
و سوف نعيش في عالم أكثر آمناً ..... شكراً جزيلاً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)